Mss.B.L968 Mss.B.L968
American Philosophical Society
John Lukens papers, 1760-1788
Mss.B.L968
American Philosophical Society
12.0 Volume(s)
There are several letters which concern Lukens' official position as Surveyor-general, but the bulk of the collection is the 12 small survey books (1760-1775, ca. 108 p.). There are surveys of Philadelphia, particularly near the State House, now Independence Square; for a vineyard plantation in the Northern Liberties (1769); and for lands in Lancaster and Berks Counties.
12 volumes, 106 p.; 4 items.
Lukens, John, 1720-1789
Box-folder 1
Volume 12
Early American History Note
The small survey books of John Lukens contain various land surveys that Lukens undertook throughout Pennsylvania. The Lukens family was a prominent surveying family with close ties to the proprietary government. The books do not contain any sketches, but are instead a listing of coordinates and features that can be used to demarcate land. Notably, there is little in the surveys about the Connecticut dispute, although items on the Lukens' involvement in that event can be found in other collections, such as the Eastwick Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from Philadelphia Autograph Company (08-25-88; $200.00) and accessioned, 1947.
Biographical/Historical note
John Lukens was Surveyor-general of Pennsylvania and was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1767.
Berks County (Pa.); Government Affairs; Independence National Historical Park (Philadelphia, Pa.); Lancaster County (Pa.); Land speculation; Maps and Surveys; Official Government Documents and Records; Pennsylvania History; Surveying -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia.; Surveying and Maps; Surveys (land).
- Papers, 1760-1788; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  Scope and Contents note
  D. 16 items.
  - Survey book, 1760; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, Sept., 1765; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, July, 1766; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, 1766; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, August, 1767; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, 1767-1768; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, April, 1769; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, 1773; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, October, 1774?; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, February, 1775; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Survey book, n.d.; 2.0 folders; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
  - Statement to the state of Pennsylvania, Sept.-Dec., 1781; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
    D. 3 leaves and add. Various sizes. Surveying charges.
  - Letter to the Supreme Executive Council of Pennsylvania, Nov., 1787; 13-1/4x8-1/4; Lukens, John, 1720-1789
    [].A.L.S.with initials. 2p. Draft. (see Lukens papers.) Concerning taking fees as Surveyor General.
  - Extract from the minutes, addressed to John Lukens, Nov. 26, 1787; 13x8; Pennsylvania. Supreme Executive Council
    Philadelphia, A.D.S.: James Trimble for Charles Biddle. 1p.and add.,end. (see Lunkens papers.) Wishes to know if he claims any fees since he became a salaried officer (Surveyor General).
  - Draught of survey of Northampton lot for Jonathan Dickinson Serjeant, May 21, 1788; 13-1/2x8; Hamilton, James, Jr.
    A.D.S. 1p.and end.: "Ret.into the Secretary's Office...for John Lukens Esqr. Edw[ar]d Lynch." (see Luknes papers.)